Previously on The Vampire Diaries:
Luke is gone. He merged with Kai.
- Kai won. - I always win.
I would've done anything. You chose death over me.
I never wanna see you again.
Bonnie needs magic to get out. We need to tell her where to find some.
Damon, you're a genius.
Caroline's mom isn't doing too hot.
Caroline was meant to be extraordinary.
And she needs to know how proud I am of her.
- You tell her yourself. - When you told me you hated me...
I think we both know I never really hated you.
She's gone.
Okay, I've got Band-Aids, surgical gear, and a medevac en route for an airlift.
You're making fun of me.
No, sweetheart, I'm making fun of me.
There is no greater first than watching your kid ride without training wheels...
- Ow! - Oh, boy.
...And no worse first than seeing them bite the dust.
All right. There.
- Mommy? - Yes?
Am I gonna die?
I would say your chances of survival are 100 percent.
Are you gonna die?
Well, everyone dies eventually, sweetie, but not for a long, long time.
But what if you die and I'm still here?
Well, then, you'll be all grown up and you won't need me.
I think I'll always need you.
Sorry, just...
- Water. - Help yourself.
So, what are you not writing?
Would you believe your mother entrusted me to eulogize her?
That's nice, I guess.
I think she was trying to teach me a lesson about my own mom.
I was supposed to do the eulogy at her funeral, and I...
We don't have to share.
Right.
I just mean...
...today is pretty much gonna be the worst day of my life.
I'm not sure I need to start it off by bonding with you. No offense.
- None taken. - Great.
Thanks for the water.
Hey, blondie.
Today isn't the worst day of your life.
Today and tomorrow, it's a cake walk.
There'll be people around you day in and day out, like they're afraid to leave you alone.
The worst day?
That's next week.
When there's nothing but quiet.
Just a heads-up.
Appreciate the tip.
Sure.
Anytime.
You've all asked what you can do to help.
There are five days' worth of projects on here.
We are going to do them in one.
We can break the rules and cut through the red tape.
Yeah. I expect my mom to be properly celebrated and buried by the end of the day.
Sure, Care. Whatever you need.
Elena. You're coming with me.
- Where are we going? - Casket shopping.
Let's move.
You drive.
I sent my car to Jeremy.
Jeremy. I forgot to put him on my list of people to call.
It's okay, I called him.
It's day 278 inside this stupid prison world.
I have two broken toes, nine blisters and an ear infection, but I don't care.
I have phesmatos'd the crap out of this magic Canadian rock...
...and I have my magic again.
And when that eclipse hits 12:28...
...I'm going home.
You hear that, me? Home.
You sure you don't want me to hold your hair back?
Stay away from me.
This is gross.
We haven't been dating long enough for you to see gross.
I have guilt. The vegan dish I made fun of did you in.
I'm dying.
Stupid Thai food.
Never again. Unh!
You know, maybe we should just skip the funeral.
We're going.
Hey. Wait, wait, wait.
Look, I know you hate me, but I really, really need to see my sister.
- I think she'll pass. - What are you doing here?
I called to tell you I was sick and you hung up.
Because I have food poisoning.
Did the sound of me vomiting on the other end not clue you in?
There's an issue I've been worried about since the merge...
...because we didn't do it right. The whole:
"You're not my twin. Hey, that's okay, close enough" plan.
But it worked, which is, you know, cool.
Hey, I'm even a bit nice now, in case you were wondering.
But I've been waiting for the other shoe to drop. And, well, I think it's dropped.
Because I'm...
Where's the bathroom?
- Oh, God. Ric. - Here.
I don't think you have food poisoning.
I was supposed to merge my magic with you, but I got Luke's instead.
Now I'm defective, and I think that's why you're sick.
I kind of feel like I'm dying, actually.
And if I die, so do you, Dad, Liv and the rest of our dumb coven.
So could you please fix me?
Like, now?
What are you doing?
Borrowing one of father's ties for the funeral.
He will skin you alive. Take mine.
Okay.
Did you finish the speech?
- Not quite. - It's an important speech.
I will finish it, Stefan.
Father said we're not to cry.
That is because Father is incapable of human emotion.
You are 10. You cry if you feel like it.
- I don't think I will. - Why is that?
Mother's angel told me everything would be all right.
- When was this? - Last night.
In my sleep. She visited me.
Did she visit you?
I must have missed it.
There. Be on your way.
I see the eulogy is coming along swimmingly.
It's percolating.
Listen, I need your advice.
And I need you to not be a dick about it. I have no one else to ask.
- This sounds promising. - What did I just say?
All right, look.
Something happened between Caroline and me.
Ooh. Finally.
And then her mom died and I haven't had a chance to talk to her about it...
...and I don't know the best way to handle it.
Oh.
Pull the ripcord.
- What? - Well...
...she's not the one. If she was, you wouldn't have to ask.
- Yeah, but I didn't even... - You've been in love twice in your life.
Setting aside that it was technically the same face...
...does this feel like that?
Not all love is true love, brother.
Caroline wants the real deal.
If you don't, then pull the ripcord before you make things worse.
Just not today.
Let her have today.
Your mother was such a vibrant woman.
Even after your father ran off with that man.
Thank you, Mrs. McGruder.
I'm sure we'll see you at the funeral.
Welcome to the world of awkward sympathies.
You have to be prepared with your responses.
I recommend at least three.
I don't know how you survived this.
The responses will be different for each category of people.
Friends of circumstance, casual acquaintances, loved ones.
I kissed Stefan.
I want to talk to him about it, but if it's bad, I feel like he won't be honest.
You know, not today.
Then talk to him about it tomorrow. You already have a lot on your plate.
I think I need to know today.
We're behind schedule. Let's go.
- Any joint pain? - Mm-hm.
- Headaches? - Yep.
Are you pregnant?
Stop making jokes.
I feel like I'm being scrunched from inside out.
This is private. Does your baby-boo need to be here?
I'm not leaving her alone with you, so deal with it.
Okay, your vitals are fine. Your temperature is normal.
I'll wait on pathology, but there's nothing medically wrong.
Yeah, duh, because I'm magically diseased.
- And you haven't puked in at least... - Oh.
Hey. Hey!
I feel better.
- Because you juice-boxed my magic. - Sorry, that was an accident.
But I... Wow, I legitimately feel better.
- You need to give me your magic. - What?
This faux merge is clearly failing.
I was supposed to get your magic, right?
I don't know, put it in a teddy bear or a bedpan or whatever and give me.
Listen. I can just as easily break seven little bones in your hand with one squeeze, okay?
I can see you're skeptical, Ric. Can I call you Ric?
Hey, buddy, but here's the thing you need to know:
Is that Jo only survives if I do, okay?
If that's not enough, the power that binds the prison worlds comes from the Gemini Coven.
If I die, the worlds collapse, all right?
I see vacancy.
Would you like me to start over with single syllables?
Did you say "prison worlds"?
As in more than one?
Has no one ever mentioned that?
This is it.
I'm ready.
There's no one to stop me.
I have magic.
The ascendant.
And the eclipse.
No.
I'm worried about Caroline.
I don't think she's handling this as well as she thinks she is.
- You're not done yet? - No, I'm not done.
And I will never be done. I am not a nice person.
I shouldn't have to stand in front of the whole town and pretend to be nice.
This is Liz having the last laugh from the great beyond.
Hey, easy.
You are nice...
...ish.
Not helping.
This isn't about you, Damon.
This isn't even about Liz. It's about Caroline and what she needs to hear.
Okay?
You missed your speech.
I know.
Why?
I could not decide what to say.
You could have just said goodbye.
- I don't really have a choice. - Of course you have a choice.
It's your magic to give or not give.
What do you think I should do?
Look, my life is full of martyrs who cave to the bad guy...
...trying to be heroes, and it never ends well.
Somebody inevitably gets hurt, or dead...
...and that somebody could just as easily be you, or Bonnie...
...regardless, no matter what you do.
So if you want to fight, and keep your magic, I will fight with you.
And if not, well, I loved you when you weren't a witch...
...and I'm pretty sure I will still love you regardless.
- Pretty sure? - At least 92 percent.
Caroline?
Doing all right?
Yeah. Fine.
You know, all things considered.
Sure you're doing okay?
Mm-hm.
Yeah.
No.
I don't know.
Just now I was supposed to put you into a category so I would know what to say...
...but then I realized I didn't know what category you would want to be put in...
...so I was thinking I guess there's no time like the horribly inappropriate present...
...to get to the bottom of that.
I could list the categories if you'd like.
Caroline, I...
I want to talk to you about all this, I do...
...but maybe when we're alone after you've had a chance to get through the day.
Yeah, God, of course.
This is not the time. I'm so sorry.
Hey, hey.
Don't be sorry.
We'll talk when all of this is over.
Care?
They're ready.
Do you need a minute?
No, I'm okay.
I'm gonna be all right, Mom. I promise.
Everything will be fine after today.
I'm ready.
Okay. Clearly I've been dropped into a snowy-tundra hell dimension.
Either that, or I've finally had a psychotic break.
- There you are. You're late. - Yeah.
Liv used to say she hated all my ties, so I had to find a new one.
- Are you drunk? - That depends.
How many days in a row can someone drink before they're just normal?
- You're not going in there. - Back off, man.
It's Caroline's mom. I'm not missing her funeral.
I'm sorry about you and Liv. I know you've been going through a lot of crap.
But Caroline does not deserve you bringing it here.
We're here today to pay our tribute and our respect...
...to a pillar of our community.
Our sister, our protector...
...Sheriff Elizabeth Forbes.
We are also here today to show our love and support...
...for Liz's family and friends.
Not only have we sensed our own personal feelings of loss...
...over her passing...
Calling Sheriff Forbes.
This is the last call for Sheriff Forbes.
No response.
Radio Number 2-6 is out of service...
...after 12 years and four months of police service.
Gone but never forgotten.
Center.
Liz Forbes was my friend.
In her last moments, she asked me to pass along a message to her daughter.
But I cut her off before she could say too much.
Told her she could tell Caroline herself.
But she didn't get that chance.
Your mom wanted you to know how proud of you she was.
And she should be.
You're a beautiful, strong woman...
...a generous friend...
...and a bright light in a sea of dark.
She said you were extraordinary.
And you are.
And so was she.
Liz was a hero to this town.
She was a hero to all of you.
And she was a hero to me.
Goodbye, sheriff.
You will be missed.
Thank you all for coming.
This is for my mom.
Good night. Thank you.
Thank you so much.
I'm sober. Don't ask me to leave.
I'm not. I'm glad you pulled it together.
The thing is, Ty, I get it, all right?
We've all been through so much that it's bound to make us a little crazy.
But I was thinking...
...you know, watching the way all those cops honored her today...
...I wanna be a part of something like that.
So I talked to one of the deputies, and he gave me an application.
There's this officer training program.
It seems pretty cool, you know, like something I'm supposed to be a part of.
I got one for you too.
- Hey. Are you leaving? - Yeah.
I think I've done the whole funeral thing enough for one day.
I'll walk you home.
No. It's two blocks. I'll be fine, Elena.
I just don't think it's a good idea for you to be alone tonight.
I think that's exactly what I need, actually.
Thank you for everything you did today, Elena.
I'll never forget it.
You're welcome.
- But... - I'll be fine, Elena. Okay?
I just had to get through today.
Oh, my God.
Let's do this.
Me, our coven and the prison worlds thank you.
What exactly is this other prison world?
A place filled with crappy people like me, I'm sure.
Congrats. You're saving their miserable lives from oblivion.
Oh. Don't look so stressed. You never liked being a witch anyway.
Shut up.
Oh, God.
I can do this.
The northern lights, the eclipse, they're both recurring events.
I can get out of here.
Come on.
Who are you?
It's done.
Thank you.
And congratulations.
Have a good life, sissy.
What did he say?
The reason I was sick.
It wasn't food poisoning.
What was it?
He said I'm pregnant.
I don't know what to say. I... Hm.
I don't know what to do with that.
Marry me.
What? No. No. That's a pity proposal.
You can't throw a pity proposal at a pregnant ex-witch.
I don't even know if I want kids, let alone get married...
Oh, my God. What are you doing?
I bought this the day after your brother died.
Caroline's mom was sick, and you were in danger...
...and I just thought life's too short.
And I've been trying to plan for the right moment...
...which was supposed to be this morning with breakfast in bed...
...you know, until you started puking up last night's dinner. Heh, heh.
Ric.
Look, we can talk about choices and all that. We can.
But I would really love to have this baby with you.
It's, uh... It's something I never thought I'd have.
So this isn't a pity proposal, Jo.
I love you.
Marry me.
I can't believe this.
Are you sure?
At least 92 percent.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Nice speech.
Thanks.
What broke through the writer's block?
I just needed to be reminded that the goodbye wasn't about me.
I failed you by not doing the eulogy at our mother's funeral.
I didn't wanna fail anyone today.
I think you were wrong.
About Caroline.
I realize that I may not be able to explain what I feel for her...
...but it is something.
And yeah, maybe all love isn't true love...
...in the messed-up way that you and I have experienced it...
...but I think this could turn into something even better.
Well, then, brother, stop wasting your time sitting here with me.
I think she could use a piece of news like that today.
I said I was fine, Elena.
I don't believe you.
All day, something has been bugging me.
You wanted to pack this all in so quickly, like you had somewhere you needed to be.
You were so concerned with getting through today...
...without a hint of how you'd feel tomorrow.
And then I realized.
You don't wanna feel tomorrow.
That's the plan, right? You're not going to feel tomorrow.
Because you're gonna turn it all off.
I thought I could get through the rough patch...
...and then just pick myself up after like I usually do.
But then Damon made me realize it's just going to get worse.
- You're listening to Damon? - I can't do worse, Elena.
Okay? I didn't even think there was a worse.
- It's better this way. - Better?
Caro... You're talking about flipping the humanity switch.
- There's nothing better about that. - That is your experience.
Okay? I have more control over my vampire self than you ever did.
My experience will be different.
It's not gonna be different, Care. It's gonna be deadly.
- You saw what happened to me when I did it. - Yeah, that's my point, Elena.
You did it.
You couldn't handle the pain when your brother died, so you turned it off.
Damon died, and you erased all your memories.
Stefan moved to Savannah and became an auto mechanic.
Do you think that you guys are the only ones who get to escape grief?
You just mentioned two of the biggest mistakes that I ever made.
Were they mistakes?
Because when you came out the other end...
...the worst part of the pain was gone.
And that's what I need.
I just need the pain to be gone.
And if Stefan had said the right thing earlier, would that have changed your mind?
Yeah, I heard.
Well, he didn't, so it doesn't really matter.
My mom is dead, Elena.
It hurts so bad I can't breathe.
I can't... I can't do worse. I can't, okay?
- I shouldn't have to. - No one should have to.
It's not fair.
It's not. I get it, I do.
I know that you think you have it all figured out...
...but please, listen to me.
I'm not gonna let you do this.
That's not your choice to make.
Where'd you go, Elena? Call me back.
Bonnie?
The one and only.
Oh, you made it.
Caroline?
Sorry to barge in, door was unlocked.
Caroline!
I don't get it.
So you were in my house in a 1903 prison world?
Watch this.
I didn't know it was still on when I got pulled out.
Congratulations. You shot some walls.
- Just wait. - Who are you?
- Who are you? - What is this?
There. Stop.
Oh, my God.
What?
That's my mother.